this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC - radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software digitalocean is the easiest
cloud platform to deploy manage and
scale applications of any size removing
infrastructure friction and providing
predictability so developers and their
teams can deploy faster and focus on
building software that customers love
with thousands of in-depth tutorials in
an active community we provide the
support you need digitalocean stands out
of the crowd due to its simplicity and
high performance with no billing
surprises try digitalocean for free by
getting a 100 dollar infrastructure
credit at doco / SC radio this is Nate
black for software engineering radio my
guest today is Gary Rennie
Gary is a core contributor to the
Phoenix framework and is a core member
of the plug team he has given talks at
several elixir conferences including at
elixir coffee you 2016 a talk called the
road to 2 million WebSocket connections
he currently works for voice layer a
push-to-talk voice communication
platform Gary welcome to software
engineering radio hi in episode 336
sasha rich on elixir we covered the
elixir programming language in that
episode we briefly discussed the phoenix
framework which is written an elixir and
today we'll discuss the phoenix
framework in more detail gary what is
the phoenix framework so if you look on
the website i think is described as a
modern web framework and as a focus on
real time and maintainability and I
guess productivity as well so you can
build your application get up and
running quickly but also as you get down
the line production you can maintain
maintain it easily as well there are a
lot of web frameworks out there so what
is it that differentiates the phoenix
framework first off
it runs on the Erlang VM which means you
get a lot of the fault tolerance that
comes with that and the error isolation
as well and then from a Phoenix
perspective the focus on real times
definitely something that is more unique
to Phoenix that you may not see in other
web frameworks and that allows you to
have like a real time web application
that updates dynamically as things
happen like for example if if a new
event comes in you can send that
straight down to the user and their UI
update appropriately when you say
real-time what are you talking about do
you mean WebSockets so Phoenix is
transport agnostic and out of the box
you get WebSockets and long polling but
there is like a behavior and elixir that
you can define that allows you to create
your own transport if you have a
different protocol that you may want to
use for an embedded device or any of
application or something okay so not
necessarily WebSockets but that is one
thing that comes out of the box I would
say WebSockets are probably what most
people will start with at least and then
you may find use cases where the other
things are appropriate but if you if you
got an old browser like maybe you need
to support ie seven for some reason then
you can use the long pooling and it will
fall back for you what is adoption like
how many people are using Phoenix and
what are they using it for so I can't
give you concrete numbers I know the
Alexa Kampf the attendance is generally
up year-on-year
and most the time Chris McCoy the
creator of Phoenix
asks how many people Phoenix in
production and the number of hands that
shoot up definitely increases as the
years go on in terms of big companies
using it I know
Bleacher Report are a big user Phoenix I
know Pinterest have a liquor in
production I'm not sure if they're using
Phoenix or not there's also Toyota
connected who are doing things with
real-time vehicle tracking and they're
using Phoenix and then I think also
Square Enix I've met some people at
conference there and they mentioned
Phoenix I think they're using as well
okay so it sounds like it spans
everything from consumer mobile
applications to automotive to
Gaming even is there an organization
backing Phoenix or who is backing
Phoenix Phoenix is an open-source
project
so a lot of the core team put their own
time into it
Chris mccords who's greater Phoenix
started on his own in his spare time but
has since been employed by Dockyard who
are an agency and they allow him to work
on it for the majority of his time and I
think he does some client work as well
but the majority of his time spent
working in Phoenix and then from the
elixir side Joe is a villain and his
company plataforma tech they also
sponsor him to work an elixir he's also
part of the Phoenix core team and plug
core team so he also spends time on
those you already mentioned that Phoenix
has real-time communication and out of
the box what are the other features that
it has out of the box
see when you get started you'll install
what is known elixir as an archive file
and that's a dependency they'll sit in
your system which will allow you to run
tasks like against your a file system so
you can run the mix Phoenix new task and
that will be the like project that it
generates for you and then when you do
that you have a few options that you can
have an epi
specific version that won't have any of
the HTML rendering parts but if you
don't set that flag then you'll have
echo in there which is a database
library we can talk about your Phoenix
core library which has all the functions
for controllers and views and templating
you'll have channels which are the
real-time abstraction there's a routing
layer to route paths to function calls
that we we have some asset compilation
but we don't we haven't written our own
asset compilation pipeline or anything
we delegate to no js' and use one of the
newer dependencies so prior to 1.4 we've
been using brunch but as of the 1.4
release which isn't released yet we'll
be switching to web pack and is there
some kind of unifying paradigm that
describes Phoenix as a framework for
example I know that some web frameworks
use the MVC model if you can
roller paradigm does Phoenix use MVC or
something else cutting them so it's
describes an MVC framework and it
certainly has views and controllers in
terms of models we we have this concept
of context and the context is a group of
related functions that contain your
business logic and they they may involve
some sort of persistence layer which
which could often be your database like
using hecto but you can also use our
Langille in or like our like as a
billing database called amnesia you
maybe aren't using a database at all
maybe it's using like ETS tables which
is our long-term storage but whatever
your case for your business logic it
goes in these contexts so for example if
you had like a common creation and user
registration then you may have an
accounts context which has functions
like register user lookup user and
that's where all that code would live it
sounds like the context is basically a
way of organizing your code into related
bits of functionality in the elixir
episode episode 336 we talked about
elixir having modules and functions so
functions being grouped into modules so
how are contexts different from a module
they're not actually that's the beauty
of them is that it's just a module that
contains functions the context is purely
a naming construct from the Phoenix side
and that just lets you have something
that you can reference like it's if you
know it's hard if you just call it a
thing so it's it's got a name we
disabled on context for it I think the
name comes from domain driven design but
it's not like a pure implementation of
design the Rangers and design it's just
taking some of the concepts why did
Phoenix decide to introduce this context
thing what is what does the context do
one of the problems were having in
Phoenix before context was the
controllers were having quite a lot of
business logic in them and they were
growing large and a little bit more
difficult to maintain and that was
because
there was no defined place to put this
functionality so people had they were
using something context like without any
formal naming but there was nothing
Phenix specific so we introduced this
context terminology as a place to put
your your functions or grouping of
functions and the benefit here is that
it keeps your controllers thin which is
one small benefit but you also then can
call all the functions that affect your
business domain outside of a controller
so elixir allows you to run an
interactive terminal using IEX so if you
have the accounts context and register
user then there's no dependency on any
of the connection information so you can
just go straight into your interactive
terminal and type count store register
user and then just type the parameters
in there like name carry whatever and
that will create a user from the
terminal or from the interactive console
you may also allow user registration
over WebSockets for example and in which
case you'd just call the council
register user function from your socket
so it allows you to build different
interfaces into your application where
the web part of it is only one one
interface what is the layout or
structure of a Phoenix program how does
it look within my ide what would I see
laid out on the file system so you'll
generate your project using the archive
I mentioned earlier and when you do that
if you don't provide any flags then
you'll have a Lib directory which is
where all your code will sit you will
have from in there you'll have two
different directories you'll have one
which is your web directory where all
your controllers and your views and
templates will go and then the other
will just be its name to whatever your
application is called and inside there
will be all your business logic which I
guess is your model and you would then
have a testing directory where all your
tests go
there's a mixie access file which is how
elixir projects define things like their
version their name maybe their
dependencies as well and by default with
Phoenix your dependencies will be the
Phoenix package on hex which is the
Phoenix library code as opposed to the
Phoenix generator code you'll have
Phoenix pub/sub which is the pub
sub-layer the powers all of the
real-time system you will have ecto at
Phoenix ecto which is a bridge between
ekdum Phoenix and you'll have Phoenix
HTML which is defines all the functions
for HTML helpers like form 4 and content
tag and you also have live reload and
development so Phoenix is generally when
you're developing live reloaded on the
web page so you make a change you'll
save it and then the browser's will
update without having to refresh and the
last thing you'll have is an assets
directory and that's where we'll
delegate to wherever your build tool is
there's a thin layer between them that
you define in config which says which
command to run to build your static
assets which I say by default be web
Packer brunch and then they'll move them
into the the privy directory which is a
part of any elixir release where your
non compiled dependencies go so it could
be like images or any fixture files you
may have go in there the first step you
mentioned was the archiver so basically
this entire directory layout was created
when you ran mix Phoenix knew and was
then put into this this folder and
optionally you had if you had if you had
not specified to exclude like the
database you would you'd have that the
ecto folder is that right there's not an
active folder but you bring in the ecto
dependency and when you do that you get
access to some of the academics tasks
there's one to like create your database
want to run migrations and the
migrations live in the Prive repo
migrations directory and you can also
like tear down or
migrate to a certain point that all
comes from active okay so ecto you
mentioned earlier was the the thing that
lets you interact with your database so
what is it is it a is an ORM an object
relational mapper or what kind of
technology is it so I guess because we
don't have objects in the link so you
couldn't classify as an ORM but it you
define schemas for ecto and you can
define queries against those schemas so
you might say this is a schema for the
users table and I have a name on there
you'd find all this explicitly in a
schema file per table and then you'll
say like my users got a name and they've
got an age and then when you interact
with it let's say you're querying and
you want all users that are over a
certain age you would bring in ecto it
goes like a query actor a query module
and from there you can call wear or
order or whoever may be so you could say
order by age where age is greater than
whatever you're looking for and from a
data modification and insertion point of
view we have active change sets and a
change set is self descriptive it's a
set of changes that you want to apply so
this the change that will run all your
validations as well so you validations
and you change that so if you want to
make sure that the users age is over 18
you could have a clause in your change
set that says the age must be great in
18 and if know you'll get validation
error
okay so ecto is not exactly an
all-around but it is some kind of
abstraction layer so then you're not
writing sequel when you're interacting
with the database but you're you're
using the ecto api yes you will define
your your queries and you you build them
up using transformations on a queryable
struct which could be if you define a
schema and you'll have like the struct
will be user in this case and that's
queryable and you can transform it using
wear and order and all the query API and
then at the end you still haven't gone
to the database yet it's not until you
call one of the functions in the the
repo module so uses the repository
pattern so you'll build up
we repoed all and that's how you
actually fetch all your users I'm not
familiar with the repository pattern
what is that so it's where you have a
module that has all your functions
actually interact with the database and
then you're building up all the
transformations before that and then
executing them against the database I'm
you mentioned rice QL as well which you
can actually use in Ector with fragments
so one sector supports a lot of the
functions you may want to use against
your your query there there are certain
things that are missing like maybe
you're using the like Jason B for
example and there's maybe not a specific
thing you need for searching on that you
can use a fragment and then a question
marks an interpolation character and
then you just pass the variables and
also has two different query syntaxes as
well so it's got one there is function
whether both function based but one is
like you call the function and pass the
list of arguments through and the other
is a bit more like I think it was
inspired by Microsoft Lync which is like
the queer engine c-sharp
so you can call things like from human
users and it uses elixir macros to write
the query it's my impression that echo
is something that you use to interact
with relational databases is that right
or does it allow you to also interact
with no sequel databases or is there
some other mechanism for interacting
with those so you can define any data
layer you want really
and it's worth knowing that you can have
as many different repositories as you
want like you configure each one
individually so there are other use
cases for that like for example you may
have a read replica and you can use a
set for a repo for your read replicas
and sometimes your query against that
and sometimes you query against your
master in terms of your data sources
it supports there's a Postgres driver
there's a MySQL Maria DB driver there's
a sequel light one but there's also a
MongoDB one and I know someone wrote a
github API wrapper for ecto so query
against so when you called repo to all
it go
query github which is quite a novel use
case I thought it sounded interesting
when you said that you could configure
it to have multiple different repos and
you could have for example one as a read
replica do you have an example of when
you had that kind of configuration that
you could use it
illustrate how that works I know
bleacher report did this because I think
needed to load bounce some of the
queries across different databases I'm
not entirely sure we use it for for that
reason so we use it sometimes if we have
a read replica in a different region for
example then we're happy to have fast
queries using the replay picker but more
expensive writes that go to the master
so a lot of our writing logic will be
configured for the main repo and then a
lot of our querying logical use the read
replica and they just have different
names as well so instead of calling a
repo to all you call read repo to all
okay so it's an explicit something
explicit in your application it's not
just part of the configuration but you
would be you'd be opting into this and a
very explicit way yeah most things in
elixir on Phoenix tend to be explicit so
in this case yeah there's no magic way
of saying these queries should go to
this database and you should go to the
other it just depends on which we
probably use at the point of executing
your query the other thing that is worth
mentioning an ecto as well is that it
has something called multi so
everything's transactional from your
query if the transaction fails then the
query will fail or the other way around
if the query fails the transactional
fail an act also is this concept of a
multi where you can define a series of
queries that all need to execute like
only to succeed for the entire
transaction to succeed and that's
transformational as well so you could
say ecto multi create user and then ecto
multi create default settings for
example and if settings fail to insert
for every reason then the user won't be
created it'll all be rolled back and
that's quite explicit as well so you
build up your multi and then at the end
you're called reproduct Ran's action the
multi is an argument okay so it sounds
like this is a way of creating
transactions in the application layer
versus just in one database you could
have
transactions that are spanning even
multiple repositories and different or
multiple repos in different databases
and also functions as well so one use
case we had recently is we wanted to
create a user and then send them an SMS
so they could you know can continue the
registration but if the SMS fails then
we don't want the user to be inserted so
that it doesn't say like your phone
number has been taken or anything and in
that case if the phone number if the SMS
doesn't send then we'll roll back the
whole thing so it doesn't just have to
be transaction and database things it
can be any function we talked to a lot
already about the data part of Phoenix
what we haven't talked about yet is the
presentation or view part what sort of
template or view capabilities does
Phoenix have the way Phoenix handles
views is quite interesting so there's a
controller which we can talk about in a
minute and they render into the view and
the view is a module and in your view
you'll define functions because that's
how you do most things and lexer and
your functions will be named render and
then you have the first argument will be
like where you're rendering so it could
be render index and then it has what we
refer to as an assigns which comes from
plug bits essentially a like a map of
values and when you render you will pass
these values to a template which is an E
X template and then the values will be
interpolated and the HTML will be sent
to the client what's interesting about
the templates is they're actually at
compile time compiled into functions on
the module so they're really quick
because at runtime you're just calling a
function and all the strings Rory there
in memory and actually uses IO lists and
serve strings which is a more efficient
data structure in Erlang if you're
sending data like to a file over a
socket could you talk about the
different content types that Phoenix
supports so plug which is the light
the Phoenix bill on top of allows you to
parse the content type and then from
there that's stored throughout the
request and then when you get to your
view which is usually one of the last
things that will happen you can have
different so as well as specifying the
action that you're rendering you can
also specify the type so you could have
render indexed or HTML and that will
render HTML and that's fine or you can
have render index at Jason and if you
return a map from there then when that
gets rendered it'll be encoded as Jason
and sent back to the client
and usually this will be explicit and
you all in your controller say which one
you want to render but there is an
option to have it lookup based on the
content type if you pass an atom instead
of a string then it will it will try and
work it out based on what plug saw
earlier what does that mean practically
doesn't mean that you could hit the same
route but depending on the content type
it would you would return JSON or HTML
or what would it mean that is what it
means and that's what it allows in
practice I haven't really seen it used I
don't use in any of my projects I tend
to be a bit more explicit and if I have
an API it's on a separate path somewhere
but it is possible for you know if you
had if you do have that use case you can
do it that's a good jumping-off point
for us to talk about controllers and
talk a little bit more about plug so you
mentioned that plug was a key to all
this and that that's something that the
Phoenix framework built on what is plug
when you're using Phoenix plug will be
very visible to you we don't try and
like hide behind it if you're using plug
then it should be obvious to you because
you'll often call plug dot something and
plug is is two things it's an
abstraction and web servers so typically
you'll start your web server through
plug and it's also an abstraction around
HTTP requests so I'll handle anything
that is related to to an HTTP request
like parsing the headers or reading the
headers sending the headers sessions
cookies sending the response status
codes and anything like that and it's
typically what you'd use in Phoenix
instead of like having a special type of
function for calling something before
you get to your controller action you
would just call plug-in there so in your
controller you may see plug a fennec
eight user for example and that will
check if the session set for that user
and if it is then it'll continue and if
not you can you can halt so it's based
upon pipelines which are series of
transformations and if any of them halt
at any point then the subsequent ones
will won't execute yes so you said that
it's an abstraction or web server is an
HTTP request what what is the
abstraction what is the the common
interface that that defines the plug so
the main thing that you'll be working
with is the plug con which is a struct
that has some twenty twenty-five
twenty-six keys and those are things
like request headers parameters the
response body and and you just transform
these as you go and they're all
functions that take a con as a an
argument and return a con as the result
so you functionally transform the struct
until it has everything it needs for the
response and then it'll send it so you
may have like let's say you've tried to
fetch a user it's failed you can call
plug Conda put status 404 and then send
response user not found but you could do
these two things in separate functions
as well if you had some some need to do
so so you can also have like for
instrumentation purposes you can have a
plug there that records a time and then
you can register before send which is
like get to execute it just before it's
sent to the client so you can start a
timer in your plug function and then
just before it sends the client you
could like record the value of the time
and then log it or whatever you want to
do with it you mentioned before that you
might have a plug function that's doing
authentication and then here you have
some instrumentation and so the request
is going through this pipeline like
first it's maybe starting the
instrumentation that's checking
authentication then it's doing
something else so it seems to be just a
list or a sequence of steps that the
request is going through is that a fair
summary yeah absolutely
so with Phoenix we tend to say it's
plugs all the way down so the first part
the you'll see in your though the entry
point to your Phoenix application will
be your end point and from there you'll
see a series of plugs so the first one I
think is like plugs static and that's
for handling static assets so they get
sent first because once you've sent a
static asset you don't need to do any
other rest of it that'll just halt your
pipeline there and then there's things
like plug ships with a few that are
useful by defaults there's one little
like generate a request ID and store it
on there one little log all your
requests either to the console or
whatever logger you've got set up on
elixir one that will force SSL so maybe
you don't want n development but you can
conditionally set that in production
Phoenix adds some as well for like
library loading as a plug for that so
that there's definitely a few and then
the last one you'll see is your plugged
up Rooter and that's a module that is
also a plug that will have its own
pipelines in there so for example for
the HTML one one um so for any HTML
based request you'll have things like
the prevent CSRF plug you'll have one
that like checks your cookies maybe and
one that checks like the the content
types valid and you may have a different
pipeline for your Jason that doesn't
need to do those things you just want to
set the format as Jason
so that would be a separate plug as well
and then at that point after it's
matched the the Ruhr gets compiled into
a big function of pattern matches and
once that matches you'll enter your
controller which is also a plug and then
that's where we started talking about
there earlier
okay so I was going to ask about how
routing works but you said that there's
a router that is also a plug it seems to
be and then that's the first thing that
determines what controller that request
goes through is that right yep so
there's a DSL that you use
that you specify scope which is like a
block of relate fun it's like a
namespace almost so you can have like a
group scope and you'll maybe have like
an API scope within your scope you can
define which pipeline you're using so I
gave the example of HTML and Jason but
you may have one that's like
authenticated requests or or something
else and you can add those to the
pipeline and then you have macros in
elixir like that we are Phoenix macros
that are all extra macros there are
things like get and post and put and
resources which will generate like your
crud actions and you specify the path as
a string and then you specify the
controller that that should go to and
then when it gets executed it gets
executed as a plug so it'll still have
the con as the first argument and any
settings is the second argument and then
that will call your controller action
I'm sorry I didn't quite understand what
the second argument was the first
argument was a connect was the con and
what was the second argument to the plug
so with plug you can have the second
argument be anything and these typically
options are related to your plug so for
example you may have a again go back to
the user authentication you may have
that and then the setting you want to
pass like the the name you want to use
when you set that in the assigns which I
mentioned is the map of values that you
can use throughout your request so
anything like if you look up anything
and you want to store that for later use
so maybe like in all your user
controllers you look up the app that's
being used first and you want to store
that on Condor signs then you could
store you can look it up then in Condor
signs that app you'd have the value that
you looked up earlier and then in your
request you can then look that up on
Condor signs you can either pattern
match it or you can just call Condor
signs that HAP and then you could use
that throughout your request and even
down to your view you can use it in your
templates as well digitalocean is the
easiest cloud platform to deploy manage
and scale applications of any size we're
moving infrastructure friction and
providing predictability so develop
and their teams can deploy faster and
focus on building software that
customers love with thousands of
in-depth tutorials in an active
community we provide the support you
need digitalocean stands out of the
crowd due to its simplicity and high
performance with no billing surprises
try digitalocean for free by getting a
100 dollar infrastructure credit at doco
/ SC radio you mentioned that the
request starts at an end point and then
goes into some pipeline depending on how
you configured it or how you wrote the
code could you run through a concrete
example so you can see how it works yeah
sure so the default end point will be
named your application web so let's say
applications called hello it would be
called hello web dot endpoint and in
there your request to come in and the
first plug here it would be the plug dot
static and if you're requesting an image
or a CSS file that would resolve and
and the pipeline be halted and
then that would be the end of your
request there's no need to go further
but assuming that's not the case then it
would probably start the logger which
would start timing the request and then
it would pars the request so that means
parsing the like request body so if it's
Jason it would Jason parse it based on
the JSON code or you you configure
that's another one of the dependencies
that you'll find you mixed ixs by the
way is like either poison or I think we
moved to Jason now which are Jason
libraries and then there will be the
session plug which we'll check and then
it's stored in the session and make that
available on plug con and then it will
be your Rooter which you define which
will be called hello web Rooter by
default and in there they'll be the
pipeline's I mentioned earlier so the
browser one the fetches the sessions and
flash messages which are like one-time
messages that exists on your next
request so in your controller for
example if you create a user you can set
a flash to say created user and then
that'll be available for your next
request and then it'll go away
and you can show that message and then
things like the cross-site request
forgery protect
go in there and then it would have the
scopes and then you go to your
controller so by default is a page
controller with an index action and then
inside your controller you will have
your actions are just functions based on
the name so in this case you'll say when
I get good for route path call the page
controller index function and then index
will be called with con as the first
argument which is the plug construct and
params as the second argument is any
parameters either from the query string
or the request body that came in and
from there you'll call render which ends
up going into your view where all
pattern match on so if you want to
render index.html you'll say render con
index.html and then that will go to your
view at which point you don't need carne
anymore you just need the assigns so
when you call a function in your view
the first argument would be the string
that you want to render so it could be
indexed or HTML and then the second
argument will be this plug Condor signs
map and in there you'll have anything
that you've set up in your controller so
maybe you've set like the change set for
example if you're using a registration
form and then that would be available on
your template so if you call form for in
your in your TX templates for Phoenix
you can use the @ symbol to as a
shortcut Conda signs so you could say
form for a change set due and then in
there you may have your text inputs and
so on and then you specify the action
you want to submit the form to and then
at that point it would send it to the
client and then the logger would finish
its timer and then it log the output to
the console or file or wherever your
loggers configured to be but by default
the console there's one bit of
terminology and dinner that I don't
think we explicitly defined it does the
action was the action there's nothing
that's speciality actually it's just a
function in a module in fact it's not
actually called the action anywhere it's
just called the function okay so what
what does it do you said that you'd pass
the template to the action and then what
what
there that's just where the the the map
gets assigned and plugged into the
various parameter slots for the for the
template or or something else so your
controller function is typically a
bridge between your context and your
your view so let's say let's go with the
register user analogy from earlier in
your create function you would say case
accounts register user or case my app
camps the register user and then you
pass it the params which was the second
argument to the controller and then
you'd probably pattern match from the
results you'd say if it's okay user then
we'll want to redirect with a flash
message that user successfully created
and if it's an error then they'll be
typically be error change set you match
on where the change set as an act or
change there and then you can re render
the same form and this time when form
four has the change set it won't be
valid and you can display like errors
for your form fields inside the like
next to the field so for example if the
user name was already taken then you
would have validated that an director
change set it's it's called a uniqueness
constraint and x2 and actually checks
against the database and then that will
come back as an error saying has already
been taken and then when you render your
form field it's a has already been taken
under there okay so this is where the
essentially the business logic of your
application happens and you you define
what happens in different cases if
you've been able to successfully
register a user you do one thing
otherwise you do something else yes
typically your context will have all
your business logic and then your
controller will just be a lightweight
quite a lightweight function that will
just match on the result of that so
maybe you've got like a user limit there
if for example like if you've tried to
register a user and maybe there's
already ten users then you may have a
function and you may like just check
before you try and go to the database
the user limit and then you may return
error user limit exceeded and you can
then match on that so you may
the atom museum exceeded where you want
to show a different error message does
not change their error it's just a
separate error wait how many user you
have and one of the things you can also
do in Phoenix is same action fallback
for your controller and that's where the
term action is is used and that is a
function if any of your actions like
index or create don't return this
construct that's required then the
function defined in your action fallback
will be called so one way you could
handle this is using with an elixir the
the way with works is you match on the
result and if the result doesn't have
that shape then it returns whatever it
did have so you could say for example
with okay user redirect with the flash
message and then return your con and if
a cons not returned then the function
you define your action fallback will be
called that can match on the errors then
so you can have all your errors in one
place you don't have to actually for
define them in your action functions in
episode 336 we talked a lot about
pattern matching but we didn't
specifically talk about the width
expression but this is something I have
seen a lot in elixir code and
specifically Phoenix code so I think
i'll refer listeners back to episode 336
if they want to know more about pattern
matching but let me just make sure that
it's clear what you're talking about
you're saying that you can define in
this with expression a list of
preconditions so the width and then the
pattern is in a way a precondition if
the result of the function on the right
hand side of that expression doesn't
match that pattern the next step isn't
going to happen and you'll go back to it
to a fallback or a default is that a
fair description yes so you can have
with can have multiple clauses so you
could say with okay user exists and they
are with okay user and then look up your
user and then okay permission and then
check the permissions do and then you
that would be your positive happy path
forever
you want to do in this case and if you
don't specify an else then it will just
return the value the didn't match the
first date didn't match so if the user
didn't exist it returned error not found
and if the permission function returned
something else it might return error not
permitted in which case that would be
what's returned but if you do define an
L so you can actually pattern match from
the results you might want to say okay I
want to do something special in the case
of error not found but for everything
else I just want to return wherever the
value was that didn't execute or that
didn't match the pattern I was expecting
okay I think that's a lot more clear and
it may sound complicated to people that
aren't familiar with elixir but my
impression was that this is a really
compact and expressive syntax that makes
things really convenient to to write was
that your impression too or it takes
some getting used to
yeah the feature is it's a fairly new
feature as well
it came in Phoenix 1 3 which is just the
latest version and it's it's just the
with construct came I think in elixir 1
3 so the Whitcomb has been there for a
while and I've been using in my code
there's a little bit of change to use it
in in a Phoenix controller but I think
it makes sense like you can have common
errors are returned in several places
and instead of matching each type you
could just call your action fallback
what I didn't want to mention in a
Phoenix controller is that you can
conditionally like when you say plug
something you can also also say when at
the end so only applies to certain
actions I think we covered all of the
major components of Phoenix other than
the real time component and you had a
really interesting talk that I mentioned
in the introduction called the road to 2
million WebSocket connections so I'd
like to dive into that example to
illustrate how the real time component
works and then also how you would or how
you did troubleshoot some of the issues
until you got to that 2 million
connections number I was tasked actually
at my company to benchmark some of the
real-time capabilities
of Phoenix and I used a library called
sung to do some initial benchmarks the
hello world of Phoenix is a chat
application because it's relatable and
it's quite easy to write default chat
application is the one I use to
benchmark and I didn't get amazing
results I think I maybe got a few
thousand connections when I tested it
locally and I was in IRC at the time and
I mentioned this and no one had really
done any extensive benchmarking on it
one of the things in Phoenix is to make
it make it like work like make the the
api's as you want them and then
performance we can kind of tackle as we
get to it and we have some confidence
that because we're using Arirang we
should be able to get the performance
numbers we want so so I mentioned to
Chris I'll do some benchmarking and he
got in touch and we got some servers
provided from Rackspace to do some
benchmarking on and we just fired up the
benchmarking code I'd written using some
you specify an XML file and the type of
test you're doing so we were doing
WebSocket testing and I think we got
something like 30k concurrent
connections on the first run so the
first time you tested this chat
application this so there's a there's an
example application that's a chat
application that's kind of a hello world
demonstration of Phoenix's real-time
capabilities but the first time you
tested it you got a fairly mediocre
result of something like 30,000
connections and then and then what
happened so we got mediocre result on
the plus side no one else would reported
the 30,000 connections as a problem for
them so at least we were ahead of you
know the people using Phoenix and we I
think Joe's a actually came in with the
first fix it was to do the way that the
messages were distributed internally and
it was it was a small chat in fact I
think it was actually just a net
deletion of code I'm not even sure if
anything was added which is quite
impressive and when we run ran the tests
are the benchmarks again with this
change I think we got to 50k connections
so it was it was good I mean it was like
what 2060 60% improvement but it still
wasn't where like for reference whatsapp
had a blog post those they had two
million concurrent connections at one
machine so we were we didn't think we
were done at 50k so for for some context
you had this whatsapp number of two
million connections and they're using a
pure airline system so they're not using
a lick sir and they're not using the
Phoenix framework but you know that just
the platform itself could support up to
two million connections on a single
machine
yeah the Machine we're using was I think
slightly more powerful and we knew that
they'd hit this two million number that
was largely down I think to the airline
VM at this point went on any like
massive shooting is just this one change
we did wha what you're supposed to do so
this is where the the long-term
maintainability comes in because Erlang
has some really nice debugging tools it
has DB G which is for tracing which we
didn't use in this instance but it's
really good you can see like when a
function is called and how frequently
functions are called and you can do that
in production as long as we're careful
about what you match on if you do too
much then it might blow up your VM but
there are libraries to help you there
but the other tool it ships with that
it's really useful is called observer
and this gives you a visual overview of
your application at runtime what we did
was we ran the benchmarks again but this
time we opened up observer and one of
the things observer lets you see is the
message queue size so I think you just
discussed it in your elixir episode but
the way message-passing works are the
way you interact with processes in
Erlang is you send messages to each
other and in observer you can sort by
message box size and what we observed is
the one of the processes the message
queue just kept growing and growing and
growing and was never going down so it
was clear from that point that there was
a bottleneck in this one process that
was the timer process
and what we went on to find was that the
way we were handling pings
to ensure that the websocket stayed
alive was using an Erlang function timer
dot send interval which wasn't the the
most performant way of doing that and it
caused a bottleneck so there's another
way of doing that process that send
after we use their and it was better and
then we realized the cowboy the
webserver we're using does it anyway so
we actually just deleted an entire
pinging code and still had same
functionality and when we did that we
got quite significant improvement I
think by the time we finished our
benchmarking on that we would ended up
with some 400 450 thousand concurrent
users on one machine so it still wasn't
whatsapp scale this point but it was it
was bear your test or your benchmark
that ye are doing was what you're what
were you measuring so the thing we were
measuring in this instance was just the
number of simultaneous connections we
could run on the machine so we had the
inbound user growth set I can't remember
the exact numbers but we had it coming
in a certain amount of users per second
and we didn't have an upper cap on it so
we just ran it until it like wouldn't
take any more connections and then we
just saw how many it would get from that
point and when you say the number of
connections this was the real time
connections so these were channels right
yes so these are all Phoenix channels
it's probably meant worth mentioning
that channels are the abstraction around
the transport which is either WebSocket
or long polling that integrates the
Phoenix pubsub which is like a way of
sending messages between clients but
also between Erlang nodes so in this
instance we only had one our Lang node
but we could have had a cluster of our
Lang nodes and Phoenix pub/sub would
have send the messages between them all
what were the client connections then
were they they were simulated
connections coming from this Tsung
testing application or how did that work
I mean the real connections but they
were idling so what would happen is they
were
would connect wait for the connected
WebSocket protocol message and then it
would just loop infinitely doing nothing
and if I think if it if it except if it
received a response then it would it
would parse it but other than that it
would just ignore everything okay but
these are real live connections and the
crucial thing in this test was that the
connection had to be held held open yes
that was the thing that we wanted to see
was how many open connections we could
have at one point and that's why they
were just idling but yeah there are
definitely real connections and you
could you could verify that as well on
the machine you like if you type netstat
and then the multitude of flags you need
to count active connections and then it
would return the 450k and eventually to
million that we we got to okay so at
this point you had 450k concurrent
connections and you're able to get to
that scale by first identifying your
your first bottleneck and that was the
thing that you were looking for was the
growth and the number of messages and
the airline mailbox that were backing up
is that something that you always look
for when you're looking for a bottleneck
or are there other indicators it's a
really good starting point certainly you
have the other indicators like CPU usage
and memory usage but to identify a
process level bottleneck the message
queue size or the number of reductions
sometimes which is like how much
computation is doing those are good
things to check you can also check your
atom table size so atoms I'm not sure if
I actually mention one atom is but it's
like it's like a string bit a constant
value so you could have the atom in
Phoenix for example we use like the atom
index for for when you call index but
these aren't garbage collected so the if
you accept atoms from user input then
this can like overfill your atoms table
user pot your memory and then it'll
crash the VM so that's another thing you
can find an observer
and one other thing that you can see in
there is your ETS tables so another
source of bottlenecks are found before
is when your ETS tables grow too large
or we're not too large but they grow in
a way that means your application slows
down for example when you're looking
them up because they've got too many
entries in them ets tables is something
we hadn't covered yet whoa what is ETS
and what role does it play
so ETS is our long-term storage it's
actually the next optimization that
happened in Phoenix when we were
benchmarking the channels it's a
essentially key value store for Erlang
terms and you can look them up based on
like what key you answer we use in
Phoenix for storing the topics so you
can look up which users are in a channel
or which channels a user has associated
you can look these things up and eat yet
sometimes you might call it ads
sometimes you call it ETS but it stands
for airline term storage and you can put
any kind of airline term in there I
would assume which would consist of what
like what was an airline term typically
atoms are used for your keys but an
airline term is like anything that you
can type in Erlang is an Erlang term so
like if you have a map of strings to
other maps that's a term like it's just
the Erlang data format okay so
effectively it sounds like ETS is a
distributed database but it doesn't it's
not necessarily persisted it's it's not
actually distributed it's it's node
local amnesia which is the database bill
on top of ATS that's a distributed
database but Ed's itself is is no local
and there's also debts which is disk
Earl I'm tired of storage and that
allows you to persist your eat yet
stable ETS table to the file system all
right thanks for that clarification
I remember from your talk that there
were there were a couple different
optimizations you made it around
and one was I believe you needed to use
at sin stead of using a different local
I think it was a local hash dict so you
instead of using just a dictionary you
used at and I'm curious why that was
important optimization I don't quite
understand you explain it just it just
happens the X is more efficient to look
up than a large map generally play off
and if you've got a map of terms that
you are storing in a gen server which is
of just a process there life then you
you'll often find that using an ETS
lookup will be more efficient and the
second optimization had to do with using
the wrong type of data structure within
ATS
explain that yeah so X has different
types of tables
it has sets ordered sets bags and
duplicate bags a bag is just a set of
not set that's the wrong word to use a
set as a set but a bag you can store
terms in but when you store them if you
have a term that's already there then it
will check for duplicates but in the
case we were doing it didn't really
matter if you're gonna have duplicates
because it was each each entry was a
unique session there wasn't a chance for
duplicates anyway so the thing we were
getting bottlenecked on was ets checking
for duplicates as it was inserting new
new sessions so we changed the type from
bag to duplicate bag and that just it
was like it was a different application
like if you look at the difference in
charts and the benchmarks we could get a
much higher rate of user per second and
we eventually got to 2 million
connections and the reason it stopped at
2 million is because the you limit we
set on the machine we set to 2 million
as like this figure that we would never
hit and and we did so so it could have
probably gone further but that was where
we stopped because of that point where
like 65 machines running it was getting
expensive what was it that allowed you
to detect
particular problem to get to that
optimization I think just isolating the
benchmarks the the person who did it was
Gaby Zuniga and he said he isolated that
section of the the application and
benchmarked it on its own and the he
discovered the bottleneck there and I
think the general takeaways is just to
know your your data types consider what
type you're using up front so for
example I think bags may be defaults
that's why it was used but you know had
the head we considered our duplicates
gonna be a problem here or not
then we may have gone to the duplicate
bag straightaway and that problem would
have existed we'll put links in the show
notes to the blog post and also the the
talk that you gave with a full breakdown
and and and all the charts are there any
other takeaways from that test that we
should talk about before we move on I
mean I think that was I think just
really think about what what your data
types are and and where your ball necks
are going to be to try and anticipate
that when you're building an application
but also I mean it's worth mentioning
that like performance isn't the most
important thing no one hit the initial
bottlenecks that were quite low and it
was until very recently that there was
some additional optimizations on Phoenix
pub/sub where I guess they were maybe
getting closer to the upper limits but
when we did have the two million
connections the the other thing we
observed was the sending a message Josie
was was trolling us and sent an entire
Wikipedia article through the channel
because we're still the web climbs
running so he could go on and you could
see the application running and he sent
like the entire Wikipedia article if I
can remember it was like the airline
programming language and it was dispute
to all the clients in in a few seconds
so that was also an unexpected part of
the benchmark sounds like you're saying
you might want to defer optimization
until you know what is you're trying to
optimize like you might you might be
sending a lot of small messages or
somebody might just decide to dump an
entire Wikipedia article but Phoenix is
able to cope with these cases but in
your specific application you might need
to
you do testing and do like tuning
depending on what type of data you're
actually dealing with I think that's
fair yeah this this specific benchmark
was very artificial like I can't think
of many practical use cases where you
need a chat room with two million people
in it but that that was the thing that
exposed these these bottlenecks and it
was a deliberate test to find concurrent
connections because it just shows like
the theoretical limit for Phoenix when
it comes to how many simultaneous users
but in a more real-world use case you
might have like thousands of channels
each with ten users or each with 20
users so we talked about the different
parts of Phoenix and we got into the
specific performance tuning example and
one thing that you mentioned was that
you're using the cowboy web server and
it reminded me that beyond Phoenix
there's also other parts of the elixir
and Phoenix eco system so what are those
pieces that maybe we haven't talked
about that you'd probably want to have
in your application or that you might
add as a dependency so cowboy was
actually written in Erlang and we're
very grateful for it because otherwise
Phoenix would have been a little delayed
by about a year once once a web server
was developed so Cowboys definitely a
dependency in Phoenix 1.4 we're moving
to cowboy - well optionally moving to
cowboy - you can use one or two in a
worker which Phoenix adapter or plug
adapter to use I'm cowboy 2 comes with
some new features like it supports HTTP
- so you'll get like hcp - pipelining so
we really leverage that and we're
grateful for that that that exists there
are other ecosystems popping up around
libraries so graph QL is one graph Gale
has its own like little ecosystem for
cell libraries around there the author's
graph QL Absinthe the graph Gale library
for elixir Ben Wilson and Bruce Williams
they've got a good book about building
applications with Phoenix and graph QL
using their absence library there's also
nerves which probably show in its own
wee
is target's embedded devices so you can
boot into elixir and maybe run on a
Raspberry Pi and it's quite common for a
device running nerves to have a Phoenix
server running for like the UI for
example the people may want to use will
include links to this projects in the
show notes I had one more question now
does phoenix include some facility for
scheduled jobs or long-running processes
or is there some library that plugs in
that does that
so our Lang has because you're running
on the Erlang VM and you can have a
long-running process you can just do it
in a lick sir so elixir has a task
module which you can use to run tasks
asynchronously and you may have a
process that says every minute see if
there's any new tasks to run or every
particular time period you want to
execute a task and that's how you'd like
a scheduled task but it depends on where
you deploy so if you deploy on servers
that you dedicated servers I guess then
things like this are fine but if you're
deploying on something like Heroku then
I know they killed spin up their images
so you'd maybe lose data there and for
those sorts of instances there are
libraries I haven't used anything
personally because I just tend to use
tasks and Jen service to schedule tasks
but there are queuing libraries
available that people have developed
speaking of deployment we could go into
that a little bit more what are the
various deployment options and what do
you recommend one of the libraries
someone has developed his name's bit
Walker of github has developed is called
distillery and that allows you to
generate a tar file from your elixir
project so it's not feeling specific but
you can generate a tar file you can
upload that tar file to your server on
Taarabt and then in there you can start
your application you run the mixed
release task and it'll compile your
your application and build the star file
for you it's for top code upgrades which
is something in the Erlang VM that
allows you to have two versions of a
module loaded and transformation
function called code change that you
transfer from the old format to the new
format distillery will allow you to to
do that when you want to build a release
it's important you also compile your
assets which is where we use brunch or
web pack but you'll want to use that
command and then Phoenix comes with a
digest command which will generate a
manifest file and version your assets so
the the caches are invalidated when you
do a new deploy
there's also Heroku build packs
available for elixir and phoenix and in
there you can specify which versions of
those you're running and then you can
deploy on Heroku however you'd normally
do so there are some elixir specific
deployment services I've never used them
I've heard of giggle ixr and I've heard
good things about that so that might be
worth checking out if you're deploying a
new elixir project are there any
specific challenges to deployment or
operational challenges in terms of
monitoring that arts Phoenix specific
you know of no there are libraries a lot
of the the big libraries have the big
services for monitoring have elixir for
like app signal does rollbar new relic
all have elixir Phoenix support you also
have all the tooling that you get from
Erlang so any airline specific
monitoring you can apply so in terms of
monitoring there's not any specific
challenges was there anything else we
didn't talk about that you wanted to
mention there's a couple of things
coming out they're exciting in the
ecosystem there's a library called
telemetry which will be four metrics
that's being worked on and there'll be
Phoenix integration for that probably at
some point and in terms of Phoenix
there's a project called fire nest which
is extracting a lot of the less
we learned in pub/sub which as I
mentioned for sending messages between
loads in an airline cluster so fire
nests will be hopefully a good way to
build distributed applications when it's
done the other new feature that's coming
after Phoenix 1.4 is live view and Chris
McCord does a good demo of this and a
good introduction to it is Alexa comm
keynote from compusa
but the gist is that Phoenix is a way
for building real-time applications
real-time view rendering without having
to write JavaScript so you can let's say
you've got I don't know a background
task running and you've got a progress
bar you can write a lick sir that will
render a small amount of HTML that will
be sent over the Phoenix channels and
that will rerender a portion of the page
with a progress bar on it for example I
see so it's doing live updates to HTML
without any JavaScript I mean it has
JavaScript but without you writing the
JavaScript I'm at that's not to say that
we're seeing no one should ever write
JavaScript ever it's just a way to add
bits of like real-time functionality
without the overhead of for example
bringing in a JavaScript framework okay
so we'll include links for telemetry
fairness and live view and the shonas
there won't be a link for live view but
you can link to the keynote which
introduces it okay will do all right
Gary um it's great having you on the
show how can listeners find out more
about you or follow what you're doing
I'm Goslar pretty much everyone the
internet except for Twitter where I was
late and I'm the gasps ler I'm most
active on those and IRC as well thanks
again Gary it's been really great having
you on software engineering radio yeah
thanks for having me this has been Nate
black thanks for listening digitalocean
is the easiest cloud platform to deploy
manage and scale applications of any
size they're moving infrastructure
friction and providing predictability so
developers and their teams can deploy
faster and focus on building software
that customers love with thousands of
in-depth tutorials
an active community we provide the
support you need digitalocean stands out
of the crowd due to its simplicity and
high performance with no billing
surprises try digitalocean for free by
getting a 100 dollar infrastructure
credit at doco / SC radio thanks for
listening to SC radio an educational
program brought to you by Archer police
software magazine for more about the
podcast including other episodes visit
our website @ SC - radio net to provide
feedback you can comment on each episode
on the website or reach us on LinkedIn
Facebook Twitter or through our slack
channel at SC radio.com you can also
email us at team @ SC - radio net this
and all other episodes of SC radio is
licensed under creative commons license'
two-point-five thanks for listening